So back in our project, if you want to use webpack there,
-: Yani projemize geri dönersek, orada webpack kullanmak istiyorsanız,
I will first of all quit my compilation and that current
öncelikle derlememden ve mevcut geliştirme sunucusundan çıkacağım
development server, and then stat,
ve sonra stat, orada webpack
make sure we can use webpack there.
kullanabileceğimizden emin olacağım.
Now since this is already a file of the package dot json
Şimdi bu zaten package dot json dosyasının bir dosyası olduğundan,
file, we can use NPM to install more dependencies
bu projeye daha fazla bağımlılık yüklemek için NPM'yi kullanabiliriz.
So simply, more third party libraries
Yani basitçe, bu projede daha fazla üçüncü parti
we need in this project.
kütüphaneye ihtiyacımız var.
And here I don't mean third party libraries which provide
Burada kastettiğim, kodumuzu kullanarak belirli işlevleri
a certain functionalities using our code,
sağlayan üçüncü taraf kütüphaneleri değil, geliştirmeyi
but instead third party libraries that help us
bizim için çok verimli hale getiren bir proje
set up a project workflow and configuration
iş akışı ve yapılandırması oluşturmamıza yardımcı olan
that makes development very efficient for us.
üçüncü taraf kütüphaneleridir.
We do this with NPM installed, dash dash safe dash dev
Bunu NPM yüklü olarak, sadece geliştirme bağımlılığı
to indicate that it's a development only dependency,
olduğunu belirtmek için dash dash safe dash
and then webpack webpack dash CLI,
dev ve ardından webpack webpack dash CLI, webpack dash dev
webpack dash dev dash server typescript and ts loader.
dash server typescript ve ts loader ile yapıyoruz.
So that's a bunch of packages and I will say
Yani bir sürü paket var ve ne işe yaradıklarını
what they do in a second.
birazdan anlatacağım.
So let's first of all hit enter and make sure
Öncelikle enter tuşuna basalım ve
these are all now all getting installed
bunların hepsinin projemize yüklendiğinden
into our project here, and thereafter we'll have a look
emin olalım, daha sonra her pakete bir göz atacağız
at each package and see why we installed it,
ve neden yüklediğimizi göreceğiz, bu yüzden bunun bitmesini
so let's wait for this to finish.
bekleyelim.
So it did finish installing for me here,
Böylece benim için yükleme tamamlandı ve şimdi
and now with that, let's analyze what we installed.
bununla birlikte, neyi yüklediğimizi analiz edelim.
In package dot json, the new dev dependencies section,
package dot json'da, yeni dev bağımlılıkları bölümü, ya
or it already existed, but now we have a lot
da zaten vardı, ama şimdi orada
of new packages there I should say,
bir sürü yeni paketimiz var demeliyim,
these packages were added.
bu paketler eklendi.
Now what do all these packages do?
Şimdi tüm bu paketler ne işe yarıyor?
Let's start with webpack.
Webpack ile başlayalım.
Webpack is the tool I just talked about,
Webpack az önce bahsettiğim araçtır,
it's the heart of this entire setup
şimdi oluşturacağımız tüm bu kurulumun
we're now going to create.
kalbidir.
It is a tool that allows us to
Kodumuzu paketlemek ve ayrıca kodumuzu
plug in certain functionalities to bundle our code
dönüştürmek için belirli işlevleri eklememize olanak
and also to transform our code.
tanıyan bir araçtır.
And that transform our code part is important,
Ve kod kısmımızı dönüştürmek önemli, burada bir typescript
we're having a typescript project here right?
projemiz var, değil mi?
Now of course we could certainly use webpack
Şimdi elbette webpack'i tüm JavaScript
to then bundle together all the JavaScript output,
çıktılarını bir araya getirmek için kullanabiliriz, ancak webpack
but it would be even nicer if webpack would do both.
her ikisini de yapsaydı daha da güzel olurdu.
Transform our typescript code to JavaScript,
Typescript kodumuzu JavaScript'e dönüştürün
and then actually emit a bundled Javascript file,
ve ardından gerçekten paketlenmiş bir Javascript dosyası
and webpack is able to do that thankfully.
yayınlayın ve webpack bunu yapabiliyor.
We need the webpack CLI to run webpack commands
Projemizde webpack komutlarını çalıştırmak için webpack
in our project, and the webpack dev server
CLI'ya ve kaputun altında webpack'i başlatan,
to have that built in development server,
dosyalarımızı değişiklikler için izleyen, bir
which starts webpack under the hood,
şey değiştiğinde webpack'i yeniden derlemek
which watches our files for changes,
için otomatik olarak tetikleyen ve sayfamızı otomatik
automatically triggers webpack to recompile
olarak sunan yerleşik geliştirme sunucusuna sahip olmak
when something changes, and which auto serves our page.
için webpack dev sunucusuna ihtiyacımız var.
And then we got typescript and typescript loader,
Ve sonra typescript ve typescript yükleyicimiz
the ts loader here.
var, ts yükleyicisi burada.
Now we already installed typescript globally on our machine,
Şimdi typescript'i makinemize global olarak yükledik,
which is why we are able to run tsc dash w.
bu yüzden tsc dash w'yi çalıştırabiliyoruz.
Now it is a good practice to auto install a copy of
Şimdi, her proje için typescript'in bir kopyasını otomatik olarak
typescript per project, so that for this project,
yüklemek iyi bir uygulamadır, böylece bu proje için belirli bir typescript
you got a specific typescript version.
sürümüne sahip olursunuz.
The advantages that if you ever change your
Genel typescript sürümünüzü değiştirirseniz,
global typescript version, you don't break your project
typescript'in kendisindeki değişiklikleri bozuyorsak
version, your project setup if there we're breaking
proje sürümünüzü, proje kurulumunuzu bozmamanızın avantajları,
changes in typescript itself,
bu nedenle bir proje için belirli bir
so we can lock in a specific version of typescript
typescript sürümünü kilitleyebiliriz, bu yüzden
for a project, that's why we installed it separately here.
onu burada ayrı olarak kurduk.
And the ts loader now is a package which will
Ve ts loader artık webpack ile birlikte
work together with webpack.
çalışacak bir paket.
The ts loader is a package that tells webpack
ts loader, webpack'e typescript kodunu Javascript'e
how to convert typescript code to Javascript,
nasıl dönüştüreceğini söyleyen bir pakettir, böylece
so that webpack is able to do both, compile our code,
webpack her ikisini de yapabilir, typescript loader'ın yardımıyla kodumuzu
with the help of typescript loader,
derleyebilir, bu da elbette
which in turn of course uses the typescript compiler
kaputun altındaki typescript derleyicisini
under the hood, and then webpack also is able to bundle
kullanır ve webpack ayrıca yayılan javascript dosyalarımızı
our emitted javascript files into a bundled js file
paketlenmiş bir js dosyasına tek bir paketlenmiş kod dosyasına paketleyebilir.
Well, and with that, let's simply get started
Peki, bununla birlikte, basitçe başlayalım ve tüm
and let's set up a webpack project so that we can use
bu güzel şeyler için webpack'i kullanabilmemiz için
webpack for all these nice things.
bir webpack projesi kuralım.